Guide to the A.J. Liebling collection, 1920-1963.
Liebling, A.J. collection, 1920-1963.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
A.J. Liebling collection, 1920-1963.
4613
A. J. (Abbott Joseph) Liebling, 1904-1963.
15 linear ft.
Manuscripts, correspondence, galley proofs, printed articles, newspaper clippings, photographs, documents, tapes, and films.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Manuscripts, correspondence, and other papers of A.J. Liebling, an American journalist who served as reporter and columnist for the New Yorker magazine from 1935-1963.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
American journalist, who served as reporter and columnist for the New Yorker magazine from 1935-1963.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Manuscripts, correspondence, galley proofs, printed articles, newspaper clippings, photographs, documents, and a few tapes and films, spanning Liebling's entire career as a journalist. The collection consists largely of typewritten drafts for hundreds of articles Liebling wrote for the New Yorker magazine, with his extensive autograph corrections, including his articles for the columns "Talk of the Town," "Our Far-Flung Correspondents," "A Reporter at Large," "Profiles," "The Wayward Press," "Fiction and Talk," "Letters From Paris" (1939-1944), "Normandy Revisited," and "Comment," as well as miscellaneous untitled articles. Also included are notes and drafts for his books The Press, Between Meals, The Honest Rainmaker, and The Pigs of St. Lô, as well as book reviews and stories he published in the New Yorker. The "Letters From Paris" articles give a firsthand account of life in Paris during World War II, mainly from 1939-1940, while "The Wayward Press" comments, often critically, on the practices of American journalism, especially in the Hearst and the McCormick newspapers.Also included are extensive notes and drafts for a book on Henry Luce and the Time empire which Liebling never published.
Correspondence includes letters from Liebling to his parents, Joseph and Anna Liebling, describing his life as a student at Dartmouth and at the Sorbonne in the early 1920's, and later letters to them which describe Paris before the Nazi occupation and London during the blitz. Other correspondents include Liebling's first wife, Ann (Beatrice McGinn) Liebling, and Jean Stafford, who became his third wife.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Liebling, A. J. (Abbott Joseph), 1904-1963.; Hearst, William Randolph, 1863-1951.; Liebling, A. J. (Abbott Joseph), 1904-1963. Press.; Liebling, A. J. (Abbott Joseph), 1904-1963. Between Meals.; Liebling, A. J. (Abbott Joseph), 1904-1963. Honest Rainmaker.; Liebling, A. J. (Abbott Joseph), 1904-1963. Pigs of St. Lô.; Liebling, Ann Beatrice McGinn.; Liebling, Anna.; Liebling, Joseph.; Stafford, Jean, 1915-
Titles:
New Yorker (New York, N.Y.: 1925); Time magazine.
Subjects:
Journalism--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--France.; World War, 1939-1945--France--Paris.; World War, 1939-1945--France--Normandy.
Places:
France--History--German occupation, 1940-1945.; France--Description and travel.; Paris (France)--History.; Paris (France)--Description and travel.; New York (N.Y.)--Description and travel.; New York (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.; United States--Intellectual life--20th century.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Large related collections of the papers of New Yorker writers E.B. White, Frank Sullivan, and Morris Bishop are also held in the repository.
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
Letters to Liebling are arranged in chronological order; manuscripts of articles by Liebling which have individual titles are arranged alphabetically by title; manuscripts of articles without individual titles (having only the title of an ongoing column) are arranged in chronological order; letters by Liebling, in chronological order; writings by others, alphabetically by author.
CONTAINER LIST
- Manuscripts
  - Between Meals (Box 1)
  - Books reviews (Box 2)
  - "...Correspondents..." 1936-1957 (Box 3)
  - Fiction and "Talk of the Town" A-M (Box 4)
  - Fiction and "Talk of the Town" N-Z (Box 5)
  - The Honest Rainmaker (Box 6)
  - "Letters from Paris"
    - Oct. 1939-Oct. 1944 (Box 7)
    - Nov. 1944-Aug. 1952 (Box 8)
    - Sept. 1952-Sept. 1960 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous factual pieces A-P (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous factual pieces R-Z (Box 11)
  - "Note and Comment" (Box 12)
  - "Normandy Revisited" (Box 13)
  - Profiles A-H (Box 14)
  - Profiles I-Z (Box 15)
  - The Press (Box 16)
  - "Reporter at Large"
    - A-C (Box 17)
    - D-G (Box 18)
    - H-M (Box 19)
    - N-T (Box 20)
    - U-Z (Box 21)
  - The Wayward Press A-M (Box 22)
  - The Wayward Press N-Z (Box 23)
- Manuscripts by others
  - A-C (Box 24)
  - D-Z (Box 25)
  - James Munves [Time notes] (Box 26)
- Documents
  - Including Publishing Agreements (Box 27)
- Outgoing correspondence
  - Family 1920-1944 (Box 28)
  - Friends and business (Box 29)
  - Jean Stafford 1915-1963 (Box 30)
- Incoming correspondence
  - 1936-1959 (Box 31)
  - 1960-1964 (Box 32)
- Correspondence
  - By and to others (Box 33)
- Reviews and articles (Box 34-35)
- Miscellaneous clippings (Box 36)
- Photographs (Box 37)
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous (Box 38)
  - New York World-Telegram, 1934 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - New York World-Telegram, 1935 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - The New Yorker, 1959 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - The New Yorker, 1960 (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - The New Yorker, 1961 (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - The New Yorker, 1962 (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - The New Yorker, 1963-64 (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - Letters to and from Ann Liebling, article regarding her death (Box 39, Folder 9)
  - Draft of Liebling's "Algerie," misc. articles (Box 39, Folder 10)
  - Drafts of "Action in the Desert" and "Earl Long-I" by Liebling (Box 39, Folder 11)
  - Misc. drafts by Liebling, "T.V. Views the Press" script (Box 39, Folder 12)
  - Misc. editorial notes (Box 39, Folder 13)
  - Misc. letters and notes for Liebling's biography (Box 39, Folder 14)
  - Misc. items including passports, note files, and notepads (Box 39)
  - New York World-Telegram, The World, 1930-31 (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - New York World-Telegram, 1932 (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - New York World-Telegram, 1933 (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - The New Yorker, 1936-38 (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - The New Yorker, 1939 (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - The New Yorker, 1940 (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - The New Yorker, 1941 (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - The New Yorker, 1942 (Box 40, Folder 8)
  - The New Yorker, 1943 (Box 40, Folder 9)
  - The New Yorker, 1944 (Box 40, Folder 10)
  - The New Yorker, 1945-46 (Box 40, Folder 11)
  - The New Yorker, 1947-48 (Box 40, Folder 12)
  - The New Yorker, 1949 (Box 40, Folder 13)
  - The New Yorker, 1950 (Box 40, Folder 14)
  - The New Yorker, 1951-52 (Box 40, Folder 15)
  - The New Yorker, 1953-54 (Box 40, Folder 16)
  - The New Yorker, 1955 (Box 40, Folder 17)
  - The New Yorker, 1956 (Box 40, Folder 18)
  - The New Yorker, 1957 (Box 40, Folder 19)
  - The New Yorker, 1958 (Box 40, Folder 20)
  - The Observer, 1955-1957 (Box 40, Folder 21)
  - Short story draft by Liebling regarding Gafsa (photocopy) (Box 40, Folder 22)
  - Misc. draft by Liebling (photocopy) (Box 40, Folder 23)
  - Misc. drafts by Liebling (photocopy) (Box 40, Folder 24)
  - Short story draft by Liebling (?) (Box 40, Folder 25)
  - Draft of Liebling's "The Girl with the Cauliflower Ear: A Romance" (photocopy) (Box 40, Folder 26)
  - Liebling's "Sur La Piste de Mollie" (photocopy) (Box 40, Folder 27)
  - Letters to family from Liebling (photocopy) (Box 40, Folder 28)
  - Letters to Jean Stafford, misc. letters and articles (photocopy) (Box 40, Folder 29)
  - Letters to Jean Staffford, misc. letters (photocopy) (Box 40, Folder 30)
  - Misc. letters from Liebling (photocopy) (Box 40, Folder 31)
  - Misc. letters from Liebling (photocopy) (Box 40, Folder 32)
  - Misc. letters and documents (photocopy) (Box 40, Folder 33)
  - Raymond Sokolov's research for Liebling's biography (Box 40, Folder 34)
  - Misc. letters and articles for biography (Box 40, Folder 35)
  - Misc. letters and articles (Box 40, Folder 36)
  - Misc. writings (Box 40, Folder 37)
  - Misc. articles by Liebling (photocopy) (Box 40, Folder 38)
  - Horse Racing Programs (photocopy) (Box 40, Folder 39)
  - Misc. articles (Box 40, Folder 40)